Kerry: As a teacher,
you're not just a teacher.
And what I think one of the strengths
of our school is that we have
such strong relationships with the
families of these young people.
And I think particularly during COVID
and these lockdown scenarios  we've
had to be more supportive of the home
environment as well as at school.
So, I know families who have struggled
with sharing time between the young
person with autism and their siblings
and feeling like most of their time is
being drawn towards that young person.
And other siblings may be sort of by
the wayside and feeling guilty for that.
I've supported families who, during
first lockdown, saw a big increase
in challenging behaviors because they
couldn't go for community access.
You know, there was no swimming,
there was no cinema, there was
no trips on the trams, which were
all part of their normal routine.
And that was a big struggle for them.
I've also supported a family who
the young person with autism was
the only sibling until she was 13.
And then mum was having a baby.
So there was, mum was worried about how
she might cope with that because she
quite liked to be in control of every
situation and things had to be just
so, and, you know, quiet when you were
told quiet and things have to be in a
certain place, and, you know, so we put
a lot of work in to why babies cry, why
they won't just shush, you know, how she
might be able to help mum, what she can
do when she's finding it a bit too much.
And that was, there was bumpy moments
and she wasn't too keen on baby brother
when he arrived, because there wasn't
much interaction there for her, but
now he's crawling and he's starting to
walk, you know, they've got a really
strong relationship that was able to
happen because we have that strong
relationship with mum and home, and
we've supported them as much as possible.
Zoe T: I've experienced the devastating
impact that autism can have on
families myself on my own family.
That's not to say that the, you
know, I'm not demonising the
autism or the child it's just, that
is, you know, it's a fact that.
I believe parents aren't supported to
properly understand the child's autism
and to properly manage the child's autism.
But it's going to have a negative impact
on many families where the child is
presenting with sort of challenging
behavior that comes as a result of
parents using, usually, using an
imperative communication style whether
putting lots of pressure on the child,
making lots of demands because they're
not understanding that actually that's
the opposite of what they need to do.